<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
	<title>Anja user's guide</title>
	<subtitle>version <verbatiminput src="../versioninfo.txt" /> aaa</subtitle>
	<author>Torbjörn Rathsman</author>
	<titlepic>
		<includegraphics src="logo_3.png" media="(max-width:128px)" />
		<includegraphics src="logo_2.png" media="(max-width:256px)" />
		<includegraphics src="logo_1.png" media="(max-width:512px)" />
		<includegraphics src="logo.png" media="(min-width:512spx)" />
	</titlepic>

	<abstract>
		<p>Anja is a sample player designed for live sound effect playback. Anja makes it possible to assign sound effects to the keys of the computer keyboard. Anja also featrues a channel mixer with 16 channels, making it possible to fade a group of sound effects together. The backend of Anja is JACK, the low-latency audio server. The session file format of Anja is in a formalized text format, optimized for human readability.</p>
	</abstract>

	<tableofcontents />

	<chapter-star id="notations">Notations</chapter-star>
	<p>The following table shows examples of notations used within this manual, or within Anja itself.</p>
	<tabular>
		<colheaders><col>Symbol</col><col>Meaning</col></colheaders>
			<row><col><includegraphics src="message_info.svg" /></col><col>The surrounding box may contain useful tips or shortcuts</col></row>
			<row><col><includegraphics src="message_warning.svg" /></col><col>The surrounding box contains information that will save you trouble</col></row>
			<row><col><includegraphics src="message_usererror.svg" /></col><col>You have done something in a wrong way. The surrounding box contains information about how you should fix it.</col></row>
			<row><col><includegraphics src="message_error.svg" /></col><col>The desired action failed. The surrounding box contains information about what went wrong.</col></row>
			<hline colspan="2"/>
			<row><col><kbd>Key</kbd></col><col>A key on the computer keyboard</col></row>
			<row><col><ui-button>Button</ui-button></col><col>A button in the user interface</col></row>
			<row><col><ui-formfield>Formfield</ui-formfield></col><col>An input field within the user interface</col></row>
	</tabular>

	<chapter id="intro">Introduction</chapter>
	<p><strong>Anja</strong> is a sample player designed for live sound effect playback. Anja makes it possible to assign sound effects to the keys typing keys of the computer keyboard. To make it easier to find sound effects, each sound effect can have a description and a color, that shows up on Anja's virtual computer keyboard.</p>

	<p>Anja also features a channel mixer with 16 channels. All sound effects are routed through one of these channels. The channel mixer makes it possible to fade a group of sound effects together. As with sound effects, each channel has a color and a description. In addition to color, description and channel gain, each channel also has an adjustable fade time, that is used to automatically fade the channel.</p>

	<p>The backend of Anja is JACK, the low-latency audio server<cite>jack</cite>. This makes it possible to connect Anja to other JACK clients enabling the creation of more complex signal flows.</p>

	<p>The session file format of Anja is in a formalized text format, optimized for human readability. The syntax of the session files has taken inspiration from formats such as Markdown<cite>markdown</cite> and is very similar to the syntax used in the "Doom template file"<cite>doomwiki</cite>. Therefore, session files can be easiliy edited by hand in a text editor, to the price of somewhat larger session files.</p>


	<section id="requirements">System requirements</section>
	<p>To run Anja, a working installation of JACK<cite>jack</cite> is required. Moreover, Anja requires <libname>libsndfile</libname> and <libname>GTK+</libname> version 3. Anja currently only builds on x86-64. Since Anja completely loads all sound files referenced from a session file, it may consume some RAM. At <quantity unit="kHz">48</quantity>, the RAM usage is <quantity unit="MiB/min">11</quantity> of sound. The minimum screen resolution for running Anja is <quantity unit="px">1024</quantity> &#215; <quantity unit="px">768</quantity>.</p>


	<section id="comparison">Anja compared to other software</section>
	<p>There are other sample players that also may be used with JACK. One such program is Hydrogen<cite>hydrogen</cite>. Compared to Hydrogen, Anja lacks a sequencer. However, in Hydrogen, waveforms need to be assigned in a particular order, and Hydrogen does not feature an on-screen keyboard. Other features in Anja is event-triggerd auto-fade, and also an exposed <em>kill all</em> feature.</p>

	<chapter id="install">Installing Anja</chapter>

	<p>Before Anja can be used, the program needs to be installed. This chapter goes through the installation procedure.</p>

	<section id="installlinux">Installing on a GNU/Linux system</section>

	<p>On GNU/Linux, the recommended way of installing Anja is to install it from the software repository. If there is no package available, download the source package<cite>anjasrc</cite>, and compile it as according to the instructions in <ref>compile</ref>.</p>

	<section id="compile">Compiling Anja</section>
	<p>Before Anja can be compiled, certain programs, and libraries are needed. These are listed in<cite>anjadeps</cite>. Obeserve that some of the libraries may be split into a runtime package, and a development package. In this case you must install both parts of the library. On Ubuntu, these packages usually have the suffix <em>dev</em>. Anja has been written using the <prgname>maike</prgname> build tool. Therefore, this program has to be available when Anja is compiled. The <dfn>makefile</dfn> distributed with Anja, tries to detect <prgname>maike</prgname> before the compilation starts. If the <dfn>makefile</dfn> fails to detect <prgname>maike</prgname>, a package containing <prgname>maike</prgname> is downloaded from the author's GitHub repository by using <prgname>wget</prgname> and <prgname>jq</prgname>.</p>

<p>As mentioned above, the Anja source package can be obtained from<cite>anjasrc</cite>. Following this link gives a link to a gzipped tarball. In order to extract that tarball issue the command</p>

	<code language="bash">tar -xf anja-src.tar.gz</code>

	<p>This will create a directory <dirname>anja</dirname>, in current directory. Now <prgname>cd</prgname> into that directory and run <prgname>make</prgname>:</p>

	<code language="bash">cd anja-src
make</code>

<p>When running <prgname>make</prgname>, files are written to <dirname>__targets_rel</dirname>. After the compilation has completed, Anja can be launched directly by running the command</p>
<code language="bash">__targets_rel/anja</code>

<infobox type="warning">Normally, Anja is distributed with pre-rendered images. It may happen that the corresponding <prgname>blender</prgname> file has been updated and the render. In this case, it will take a much longer time than normal to compile Anja, since the images will need to be rerendered.</infobox>

	<p>To make it easier to launch Anja, you can move it to a place mentioned in the <env>PATH</env> variable. For example, if you have <prgname>sudo</prgname> permissions, you can do</p>
<code language="bash">sudo mv __targets_rel/anja /usr/local/bin</code>
<p>If you do not have <prgname>sudo</prgname> permissions, you can move it to <dirname>~/bin</dirname> instead:</p>
<code language="bash">mv __targets_rel/anja ~/bin</code>

	<chapter id="using">Using Anja</chapter>

	<p>Starting Anja brings up a window that looks like the one presented in <ref>anjastart</ref>. The workspace consits of four main parts outlined in <ref>anjaworkspace</ref>. At the top, there is a <dfn>status area</dfn>, showing the state of Anja. Below that, there are two columns. The leftmost column contains the <dfn>action panel</dfn> with different buttons that affect Anja's current state. To the right of that, the <dfn>keyboard view</dfn> is located, and below that, there is a <dfn>settings panel</dfn>, controling which waveforms are loaded as well as the playback of loaded waveforms.</p>

	<figure id="anjastart">
		<includegraphics src="mainwindowstart.png" />
		<caption>The Anja window, as shown after launching Anja without any command line arguments, and with a JACK server running.</caption>
	</figure>

	<figure id="anjaworkspace">
		<includegraphics src="anja_layout.svg" />
		<caption>The different parts of the Anja workspace. At the top, there is a <dfn>status area</dfn> showing the state of Anja. To the left is the <dfn>action panel</dfn>, used to control Anja's state. To the right is the <dfn>keyboard view</dfn>, which selects waveform slots and channels, and below that is the <dfn>settings panel</dfn>, which is used to load waveforms and control the playback of loaded waveforms.</caption>
	</figure>

	<p>The different parts of the <dfn>settings panel</dfn> will be covered later. The <dfn>status area</dfn>, shown larger in <ref>statusareacut</ref>, contains three parts as illustrated by <ref>statusareafig</ref>. The leftmost panel shows the status of the engine, and the rightmost panel shows the state of the computer keyboard. Between these, the state of all ports are shown.</p>

	<figure id="statusareacut">
		<includegraphics src="statusarea.png" />
		<caption>A detailed view of the <dfn>status area</dfn>. The <dfn>status area</dfn> contains four panels: An engine status indicator, port status indicators, a keyboard status indicator, and a memory usage indicator.</caption>
	</figure>

	<figure id="statusareafig">
		<includegraphics src="statusarea.svg" />
		<caption>Layout description of the <dfn>status area</dfn>.</caption>
	</figure>

<p>The engine status and the keyboard status indicators should be self-explanatory: red <includegraphics src="led_stop.png"/> means that it is not ready, and green <includegraphics src="led_ready.png"/> that it is ready. A similar convention holds for the <dfn>port status area</dfn> (see <ref>chstatus</ref> for more details). In addition to being in the state of usable or not usable, ports are of different types: MIDI or Wave, input or output. MIDI ports have red-shaded background, while Wave ports have a blue-shaded background. Input ports are located to the left, and output ports are located to the right. Between the input and output sections, there are indicators with neutral background. These represent the 16 internal Wave ports.</p>

<p>The memory usage indicator uses high-saturated colors for memory used by the current instance of Anja. The amount of memory used by other processes uses low-saturated colors. The level indicator is divided into two parts: RAM and swap. The RAM part is green, while the swap part is red.</p>

<infobox type="warning">You do <em>not</em> want Anja to spill over into the swap space, since it can result in long delays between pressing triggering playback, and actual sound output. Also, it can result in sound dropout from other processes running on the same JACK server.</infobox>

<section id="addfx">Loading a waveform</section>
	<p>To load a waveform, choose a slot by clicking on the corresponding key in the <dfn>keyboard view</dfn> (see <ref>anjaworkspace</ref>). It is possible to choose any typing key except system keys and the space bar. After choosing a key <kbd><var>K</var></kbd>, the corresponding key will be highlighted. Now click <ui-button>Browse…</ui-button> to the right of <ui-formfield>Source</ui-formfield> field now visible in the <dfn>settings panel</dfn> (see <ref>anjastart</ref>). This brings up a file selection dialog. It is also possible to type a filename directly in the text input field to the left of <ui-button>Browse…</ui-button>.</p>

	<infobox type="info">In case a multi-channel audio file is loaded, only the data for the first (usually the "left" channel) will be loaded. This is because Anja uses mono waveforms. For information about playing multi-channel audio, see <ref>multichannel</ref>.
	</infobox>

	<section id="play">Playing waveforms</section>
	<p>Before any sound can be heard from Anja, the following conditions has to be met:</p>

	<ul><li>The <dfn>audio engine</dfn> has to be running</li>
	<li>The output of Anja has to be connected to a suitable system playback port</li>
	<li>The corresponding playback channel (see <ref>pbchannel</ref>) has to be unmuted, and have a non-zero gain.</li>
	<li>The workspace must accept keyboard input (see <ref>keybstatus</ref>), or the MIDI input port must be connected to a MIDI event source (see <ref>midi</ref>)</li></ul>

<subsection id="engstatus">Controlling and manipulating engine status</subsection>

	<p>As stated above, the state of the engine is showed by the leftmost panel in the <dfn>status area</dfn>. If a JACK server was already running when Anja was started, the engine should be running already. Otherwise, make sure that there is a JACK server running, and click the button <ui-button>Start engine</ui-button> in the <dfn>action panel</dfn>. Now, there should be a new JACK client with a name that derived from the name of the current Anja session. For example, after starting the engine on the default session, there should be a JACK client called <env>New session.anja</env>.</p>

<subsection id="connections">Connecting Anja to system playback</subsection>
	<p>By default, Anja has two output ports: <dirname>Master out</dirname> and <dirname>Audition</dirname>. The difference between these ports is what sound that are routed to them. <dirname>Master out</dirname> is the main output, in the sense that all playback triggered by regular key input and MIDI (see <ref>midi</ref>) will be routed to this port. The <dirname>Audition</dirname> port is used for playback of the current slot (in <ref>addfx</ref> the slot mapped to key <kbd><var>K</var></kbd>), triggered by hitting <kbd>Space</kbd>.</p>

	<infobox type="info">
	Notice that hitting <kbd>Space</kbd> bar will never output any sound to <dirname>Master out</dirname>. This makes it possible to prelisten to sounds without routing them to a PA system.
	</infobox>

<p>The connection status of <dirname>Master out</dirname> and <dirname>Audition</dirname> is shown by the two indicators with blue-shaded background in the output section of the <dfn>port status area</dfn> (see <ref>statusareacut</ref> and <ref>statusareafig</ref>). When the engine is not running, these are black <includegraphics src="led_off.png" />. When the engine is running, a non-connected port is indicated by a yellow <includegraphics src="led_wait.png" /> light, and a connected port is indicated by a green <includegraphics src="led_ready.png"/>. For more details about port status indicators, see <ref>chstatus</ref>.</p>

<figure id="portselector">
	<includegraphics src="portselector.png" />
	<caption>The port selection dialog. To route the signal to a port, toggle the corresponding button. The choices are confirmed by clicking <ui-button>OK</ui-button>.</caption>
</figure>

<p>A port can be connected to other ports in the system by clicking on the corresponding status indicator. This brings up a dialog box that contains toggle buttons for all availible ports (see <ref>portselector</ref>). Click <ui-button>OK</ui-button> to confirm your choicee.</p>

<infobox type="info">JACK ports can be connected by using the command <prgname>jack_connect</prgname><cite>manjack</cite>. To connect the mentioned ports to a pair of system playback ports. the commands would be
<code language="bash">jack_connect 'New session.anja:Master out' 'system:playback_1'
jack_connect 'New session.anja:Audition' 'system:playback_2'
</code>
Then, Anja will use the "Left" channel as main output, and the "Right" channel as Audition.</infobox>

<infobox type="info">Instead of using the command line, it is possible to use a JACK patchbay tool such as <prgname>Catia</prgname><cite>catia</cite>. In <prgname>Catia</prgname> ports can be connected using "Drag and drop".</infobox>


<subsection id="keybstatus">Activating the keyboard</subsection>
<p>Since the keyboard is shared between the playback triggering system and form input fields, playback can only be triggered from the keyboard when keyboard triggering is active. The <dfn>keyboard status indicator</dfn> (see above) is red <includegraphics src="led_stop.png"/> when a form input field has keyboard focus, and green <includegraphics src="led_ready.png"/> when playback triggering is active. Keyboard triggering is activated by hitting <kbd>ESC</kbd>, or by clicking anywhere on the workspace that would not capture keyboard focus.</p>

<section id="rec">Capturing waveforms</section>
<p>Similar to waveform playback (see <ref>play</ref>), waveform capture requires that the audio engine is started. In order to capture a waveform, make sure that <dirname>Wave in</dirname> is connected to a signal source. The indicator for <dirname>Wave in</dirname> is the leftmost indicator in the <dfn>port status area</dfn>. Then press <kbd>Ctrl</kbd> and the typing area key <kbd><var>K</var></kbd> that should be used for playing the captured waveform. If the <kbd>Ctrl</kbd> is released before the typing area key, playback of the recorded waveform is triggered. If <kbd><var>K</var></kbd> is released first, the capture process is stoppped.</p>

<infobox type="info">Triggering audio capture from the computer keyboard is only possible when keyboard triggering is active. When it is active, the <dfn>keyboard status indicator</dfn> is green <includegraphics src="led_ready.png"/>. Otherwise, it is red <includegraphics src="led_stop.png"/>.</infobox>

<infobox type="info">It is not possible to record waveforms to a slot that has been marked as read-only. See <ref>waveformprop</ref> form more information.</infobox>

<infobox type="warning">Captured waveforms are stored the waveform in virtual memory. This means that it is not possible to record longer waveforms. Also, trying to do so may crash Anja. See <ref>requirements</ref> for information about memory requirements.</infobox>

<section id="waveformprop">Configuring waveform playback</section>
<p>The playback behaviour and other properties can be controlled through the <dfn>waveform tab</dfn> in the <dfn>settings panel</dfn> (see <ref>anjaworkspace</ref>). An enlarged view of the <dfn>waveform tab</dfn> after loading a waveform file is shown in <ref>waveformsettings</ref>. This view is activated by clicking on the corresponding key on the keyboard view.</p>

<figure id="waveformsettings">
	<includegraphics src="waveformsettings.png" />
	<caption>An enlarged view of the <dfn>settings panel</dfn> showing the <dfn>waveform tab</dfn>, after loading a waveform file. This tab contains various settings controlling playback of the selected slot.</caption>
</figure>

<subsection id="wavesource">Source file selection</subsection>
<p>The source file is chosen through the <ui-formfield>Source</ui-formfield> field. By clicking <ui-button>Browse…</ui-button>, a file selection dialog appears. When a different wave file is selected Anja replaces the waveform associated with current slot, with the waveform loaded from the chosen file. For information about supported file formats, see <ref>fileformats</ref>.</p>

<infobox type="info">
	It is not possible to load another waveform when the current slot is in use by the engine.
</infobox>

<infobox type="info">
	Changing the source file on disk without clicking on the reload button <ui-button>↺</ui-button> does not affect Anja, since Anja loads a copy of the file content into memory.</infobox>

<infobox type="warning">
	Avoid loading large files. Doing so, may exhaust system memory. See <ref>requirements</ref> for information about memory requirements.
</infobox>

<subsection id="description">Waveform description</subsection>
<p>It is possible to assign an arbitrary description to the waveform slot through the <ui-formfield>Description</ui-formfield> field. The description does not affect the waveform playback, but makes it easier to find the waveform in the <dfn>Keyboard view</dfn>.</p>

<p>It may happen that the description is long. Therefore it is possible to mark a key-phrase by surrounding it with square brackets. Then, only the text within the first pair of square brackets will appear at the virtual key. If there are no square brackets within the description, the first word will be used instead.</p>

<subsection id="wavecolor">Waveform color</subsection>
<p>Like description (see <ref>description</ref>), the <ui-formfield>Color</ui-formfield> field is only used for visual enhancements. The color is given as red-green-blue-alpha values delimited by <char>;</char>, where each component is in the range [0, 1]. If the <ui-button>…</ui-button> is pressed, a color selection dialog based on the HSL color system appears.</p>

<infobox type="info">
	The idea behind color coding of waveform slots is that slots that are used in similar context can be encoded with a similar color. The color coding feature can be used to categorize different kinds of waveforms such as <var>Fx</var>  and <var>Ambient</var>.
</infobox>

<subsection id="pbchannel">Playback channel</subsection>
<p>The <ui-formfield>Channel</ui-formfield> field assigns a channel to the waveform slot. All sound from this slot will be routed through the selected channel.</p>

<infobox type="info">
	Channels can be used to fade multiple sound sources together. The mix of all channels can either be controlled by the internal <dfn>channel mixer</dfn> (see <ref>chmixer</ref>), or by an external mixer (see <ref>sessprop</ref>).
</infobox>

<subsection id="pbgain">Playback gain</subsection>
<p>Before the signal reaches the strip for the selected playback channel (see <ref>pbchannel</ref>), the signal is amplified by the given playback gain. The gain can be adjusted from <quantity unit="dB">-72</quantity> to <quantity unit="dB">6</quantity>.</p>

<subsection id="pbgainrandom">Playback gain randomization</subsection>
<p>In addition to deterministic playback gain adjustment, it is possible to add a non-deterministic component to the playback gain. The  parameter <ui-formfield>Gain random</ui-formfield> sets how much the random component is amplified.</p>

<infobox type="info">Depending on the state of the <ui-formfield>Set gain on loop</ui-formfield> flag (see <ref>pboptgainrand</ref>), new random numbers are drawn on manual re-triggering, or for each iteration when playback loop is active. This can be useful for creating a more "living" sound.</infobox>

<subsection id="pboptions">Controlling playback behavior</subsection>
<p>There are different options for controlling the playback behavior. These are <dfn>Loop</dfn>, <dfn>Sustain</dfn>, <dfn>Readonly</dfn>, and <dfn>Set gain on loop</dfn>.</p>

<subsubsection id="pboptloop">Loop</subsubsection>
<p>When <dfn>Loop</dfn> is enabled, playback will start form the <dfn>loop begin cursor </dfn> when the playback position reaches the <dfn>loop end cursor</dfn>, if no stopping event has occurred before that happens. For more information about adjusting cursors, see <ref>rangeadjust</ref>.</p>

<subsubsection id="pboptsustain">Sustain</subsubsection>
<p>The <dfn>Sustain</dfn> flag controls whether or not a key release event should also send a stop event. When the <dfn>Sustain</dfn> flag is set, a stop event is not sent, emulating the effect of a pushed sustain pedal. </p>

<subsubsection id="pboptreadonly">Readonly</subsubsection>
<p>The <dfn>Readonly</dfn> flag controls whether or not it is possible to overwrite a loaded waveform with captured audio (see <ref>rec</ref>). Enabling <dfn>Readonly</dfn> prevents that a loaded waveform is accidentally overwritten by a record command.</p>

<subsubsection id="pboptgainrand">Set gain on loop</subsubsection>
<p>As mentioned in <ref>pbgainrandom</ref>, it is possible to only randomize gain on the trig event, but it is also possible set a new gain for each iteration in a loop. When this flag is set, the latter happens.</p>

<subsection id="rangeadjust">Adjusting playback or loop range</subsection>
<p>It may happen that only a part of a loaded waveform is interesting for playback or loop. With the <dfn>trim panel</dfn> (see <ref>trimpanel</ref>), it is possible to select the part of the waveform that should be played or looped. The graph shows in dB<sub>FS</sub>, the root mean square signal power integrated over <quantity unit="ms">1</quantity>, as a function of time in seconds. On top of the function graph, there are four cursors showing playback and loop range, as well as the <dfn>auto-trigger threshold level</dfn>. In addition to the plot window, there are four input fields that can be used to set playback cursor positions by entering the corresponding time position in seconds. The leftmost input field <ui-formfield>↦</ui-formfield> sets the <em>begin</em> position. The next input field, <ui-formfield>↪</ui-formfield>, sets the <em>loop begin</em> position. The next two input fields, <ui-formfield>↩</ui-formfield> and <ui-formfield>⇥</ui-formfield>, controls <em>loop end</em> and <em>end</em> respectively. Between the <em>begin</em> part and <em>end</em> section is a toggle button that toggles reversed playback.</p>

<figure id="trimpanel">
	<includegraphics src="waveformtrim.png" />
	<caption>The <dfn>trim panel</dfn>. Together with cursor postions, the plot window shows in dB<sub>FS</sub>, the root mean square signal power integrated over <quantity unit="ms">1</quantity> as a function of time in seconds. Below the plot window there are four input fields that sets the positions of the playback cursors. </caption>
</figure>

<infobox type="info">
Notice that when a cursor is located at the same position as another cursor, it might be obscured by the other cursor. This is why there are only three cursors visible in <ref>trimpanel</ref>.
</infobox>

<figure id="playseq">
	<includegraphics src="playseq.svg" />
	<caption>The playback sequence. Playback starts at the <em>begin</em> cursor and passes the <em>loop begin</em> cursor. When the playback position reaches the <em>loop end</em> cursor, and loop is activated and the engine has not received a stop message, the playback will continue from <em>loop begin</em> when it reaches <em>loop end</em>. Otherwise, playback continues until <em>end</em> is reached, or a stop message is received.</caption>
</figure>

<p>Before going into the details on how to set playback and loop ranges, it is good to get an overview of the playback sequence illustrated in <ref>playseq</ref>. Playback starts at the <em>begin</em> cursor and passes the <em>loop begin</em> cursor. When the playback position reaches the <em>loop end</em> cursor, and loop is activated and the engine has not received a stop message, the playback will continue from <em>loop begin</em> when it reaches <em>loop end</em>. Otherwise, playback continues until <em>end</em> is reached, or a stop message is received.</p>

<infobox type="warning">If the <em>loop begin</em> cursor coincides with <em>loop end</em> cursor, the loop range becomes empty and there will be no audible loop.
</infobox>

<subsubsection id="cursorpositions">Setting cursor positions</subsubsection>
<p>The primary way of setting the position of a cursor is to drag the cursor into position. The position of the <em>begin</em> is controlled by the green solid cursor and the position of the <em>loop begin</em> is controlled by the green dashed cursor. The end cursors are drawn the same way but in red instead of green.</p>

<infobox type="info">If it is hard to position a cursor sufficently exact, try pressing <kbd>Ctrl</kbd> or <kbd>Shift</kbd> while using the mousewheel. This will zoom in or out in the <var>x</var> or <var>y</var> directions. Draging inside the plot window, but not near a cursor, will translate the view window. Right-clicking in the plot window will reset the view to its initial state.
</infobox>

<p>Another way of adjusting the cursor positions is to drag the auto-triggering cursor while pressing <kbd>Shift</kbd>. This will move the <em>begin</em> and <em>end</em> cursors to the first or last position where the signal power exceeds the current threshold level. If this requires that the loop cursors to move, they will be pushed by the non-loop cursors.</p>

<infobox type="info">It is possible to use the auto-trigger threshold to set both the playback range and the loop range individually as long as the loop range is set given a higher threshold level. Since the auto-trigger only moves the <em>begin</em> and <em>end</em> cursors, but doing so may push the loop cursors to new positions, it is possible to push the loop cursors inwards to a certain position. When lowering the auto-trigger threshold, the loop cursors stays, but the other cursors move outwards.
</infobox>

<infobox type="info">If <kbd>Shift</kbd> is not pressed when the auto-triggering cursor is moved, no automatic adjustment is applied. This way, the auto-triggering cursor can be used as a guide for positioning the cursors manually.
</infobox>

<p>A third option is to enter cursors positions into the input fields below the plot window. The leftmost input field <ui-formfield>↦</ui-formfield> sets the <em>begin</em> position. The next input field, <ui-formfield>↪</ui-formfield>, sets the <em>loop begin</em> position. The next two input fields, <ui-formfield>↩</ui-formfield> and <ui-formfield>⇥</ui-formfield>, controls <em>loop end</em> and <em>end</em> respectively.</p>

<subsubsection id="revplayback">Reversed playback</subsubsection>
<p>Reversed playback is toggled by the middle button in the <dfn>trim panel</dfn> (see <ref>trimpanel</ref>). What it does is to swap the direction shown in <ref>playseq</ref> by reversing the list of cursor.  Another way of enabling reversed playback is to manually position the <em>end</em> cursors before the <em>begin</em> cursors. When <em>begin</em> and <em>end</em> cursors meats, the reverse toggle button changes state.</p>
<!--
<section id="chmixer">Configuring playback channels</section>

<p>The <dfn>Channel mixer</dfn> is shown in <ref>channelmixerfig</ref>. The <dfn>Channel mixer</dfn> controls the playback volume for the different playback channels. To the right of all channel strips, there is a master gain control, which controls the playback volume of the mixed channels. In addition to a gain control, each channel strip also contains an input field for selecting a channel color, which works similar to the color input field for waveforms (see <ref>wavecolor</ref>), and a control for determining the <dfn>time constant</dfn> for automatic fade-in/out.</p>

<figure id="channelmixerfig">
	<includegraphics src="anjamixer.png"/>
	<caption>The <dfn>Channel mixer</dfn>. Each channel strip has a label, a color, a fade time knob, and a volume slider. To the right of all strips, there is a master gain control, that affects the gain of the mix.</caption>
</figure>

<infobox type="info">
	It may be a good idea to match the channel colors in some way to the colors used for the waveform associated with the playback channel. This makes it easier to find the right channel strip in the <dfn>Channel mixer</dfn>.
</infobox>

<infobox type="info">
	The knob for controlling the <dfn>time constant</dfn> for auto-fade works in polar coordinates. If it is hard to find the right value, try to increase the distance to the knob center when adjusting the corresponding value
</infobox>

<p>Automatic fade-in/out is triggered by hitting <kbd>F<var>k</var></kbd> while pressing <kbd>↑</kbd>/<kbd>↓</kbd>, where <var>k</var> is the channel number. After fade-out, the channel is muted until it is unmuted or a fade-in occures. Mute and unmuting a channel is done by hitting the corresponding channel key (<kbd>F<var>k</var></kbd>) while pressing <kbd>←</kbd> or <kbd>→</kbd> respectively.</p>

<infobox type="info">
	It is only possible to access channel 1 to 12 from the PC keyboard. In order to auto-fade channel 13-16, an external MIDI controller can be used, see <ref>midi</ref>.
</infobox>

<infobox type="info">
	Using the PC keyboard to trigger fade-in/out is only possible when the <dfn>Keybord view</dfn> is active.
</infobox>

<section id="multichannel">Multi-channel output</section>

<p>Anja has the option to use individual channel output. This enables the use of external effect processors on the different channels. The option is activated by checking the checkbox <ui-button>Use individual ports for each channel</ui-button> in the <dfn>Session properties</dfn> (see <ref>sessprops</ref>) panel. When individual ports are used for different channels, Anja creates one JACK port for each of the 16 channels in addition to <dirname>Master out</dirname>. The signal sent to these channels are taken after the corresponding channel strip, but before the master gain adjustment.</p>

<p>If the split signal needs to be mixed before sent to another JACK client, it is possible to connect all ports to the same input port. In this case, it might be good to use <prgname>non-mixer</prgname> to adjust the total output gain.</p>

<infobox type="info">
	Toggeling multi-channel output requires the engine to be restarted.
</infobox>

<section id="sessprops">Modifying session properties</section>
<p>The <dfn>Session properties panel</dfn>, shown in <ref>sesspropspanel</ref>, contains some session-wide settings. The <ui-formfield>Title</ui-formfield> is used to identify the session in the JACK patchbay. It is also possible give the session short <ui-formfield>Description</ui-formfield> that describes the session further. Anja also has the possibility to use different output ports for the different internal channels by enabling <ui-button>Use individual ports for each channel</ui-button>. This feature is described further in <ref>multichannel</ref>.</p>

<infobox type="info">
	Both toggling multi-channel output and setting a new title requires the engine to be restarted.
</infobox>

<figure id="sesspropspanel">
	<includegraphics src="anja-sessionprops.png"/>
	<caption>The <dfn>Session properties panel</dfn>. From this panel, it is possible to give the session a title and a description, as well as enabling multi-channel output (see <ref>multichannel</ref>). </caption>
</figure>


<section id="midi">Using MIDI</section>
<p>MIDI is a standard for communications between musical instruments, and other equipment<cite>mma</cite>. Through MIDI, Anja can be controlled by another MIDI enabled device or software. Anja can also be used to controll other MIDI enabled devices or software applications.</p>

<subsection id="midi_in">Controlling Anja with other devices or software applications</subsection>

<p>Before Anja can be controlled, the corresponding <dirname>MIDI in</dirname>, to the MIDI output of the device or software application that should be used to controll Anja. For control from other hardware, a suitable output port is usually <dirname>midi_capture_1</dirname>.</p>

<subsection id="midi_out">Using Anja to control other devices or software applications</subsection>

<p>A suitable input port for controlling external devices is usually <dirname>midi_playback_1</dirname>.</p>
-->

	<bibliography>
		<item id="anjasrc">Anja source archive <url>https://github.com/milasudril/anja/releases/latest</url></item>
		<item id="anjadeps">Anja sample player: Dependencies <url>https://github.com/milasudril/anja#dependencies</url></item>
		<item id="jack">JACK Audio Connection Kit <url>http://jackaudio.org</url></item>
		<item id="markdown">Daring Firball: Markdown <url>https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown</url></item>
		<item id="doomwiki">Doom file template <url>http://doom.wikia.com/wiki/Doom_file_template</url></item>
		<item id="hydrogen">Hydrogen <url>http://www.hydrogen-music.org/hcms</url></item>
		<item id="manjack"><prgname>jack_connect</prgname> manual page</item>
		<item id="catia">... <url>http://kxstudio.org</url></item>
		<item id="mma">MIDI Association <url>http://midi.org</url></item>
	</bibliography>

<appendix />

<chapter id="chstatus">Port status indicators</chapter>
<p>This table shows all states the port status indicators can have.</p>
<tabular>
	<colheaders><col>Indicator</col><col>Meaning</col></colheaders>
	<row><col><includegraphics src="led_off.png" /></col><col>Engine is not running</col></row>
	<row><col><includegraphics src="led_off.png" /></col><col>Channel is muted, and not connected to any port</col></row>
	<row><col><includegraphics src="led_wait.png" /></col><col>Channel is unmuted and not connected to any port</col></row>
	<row><col><includegraphics src="led_stop.png" /></col><col>Channel muted, and connected to some port</col></row>
	<row><col><includegraphics src="led_ready.png" /></col><col>Channel unmuted and connected to some port</col></row>
</tabular>

<chapter id="cmdopts">Command line options</chapter>
	<p>It is possible to control how Anja is started from the command line. The general syntax is</p>

	<code language="bash">anja [OPTIONS] [--] session</code>

	<p>All possible options are listed in <ref>cmdoptstab</ref>.</p>

	<table id="cmdoptstab">
		<caption>Command line options for Anja</caption>
		<tabular>
			<colheaders><col>Option</col><col>Description</col></colheaders>
			<row><col>--about</col><col>prints an about message to standard output and exits</col></row>
			<row><col>--dark</col><col>starts Anja in dark mode. This is default.</col></row>
			<row><col>--fullscreen</col><col>starts Anja in fullscreen mode</col></row>
			<row><col>--light</col><col>starts Anja in light mode</col></row>
			<row><col>--windowed</col><col>starts Anja in windowed mode. This is default.</col></row>
			<row><col>--help</col><col>prints a summary of command line options to standard output and exits</col></row>
		</tabular>
	</table>

	<chapter id="fileformats">Supported file formats</chapter>
	<p>Anja uses <libname>libsndfile</libname> in order to load wave files. Thus the file formats supported by Anja, are the same as the file formats supported by <libname>libsndfile</libname>.</p>

</document>
